Mo Willems Papers 2008.0032
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Mo Willems Papers
undated, 1965-2007.
2008.0032
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
23.5 Linear feet
The collection contains materials dating from Willems' childhood to 2007, with correspondence, artwork, photographs, notes, manuscripts, moving images in the form of films and tapes, toys, fan mail, and publications. There are also several puzzles, sketchbooks, and materials created during his college days. The collection also contains a small drafting table used by Willems and annotated with the books he used the table to create.
Willems, Mo.
Biography
Mo Willems, born February 11, 1968, and raised in New Orleans. He attended the Isidore Newman School and graduated cum laude from New York University's Tisch School of the Arts. His 2006 book, You can never find a rickshaw when it monsoons, was the result of a year spent travelling the world where he drew a cartoon a day. From 1993-2002 Willems worked as a writer and animator for Sesame Street, winning six Emmys. Willems has won major awards in a short amount of time; his books Don't let the pigeon drive the bus (2004), Knuffle Bunny: a cautionary tale (2005), and Knuffle Bunny too: A case of mistaken identity (2008) all won Caldecott Honors. Books in his Elephant and Piggie series have won two Geisel Medals and a Geisel Honor. Two animated shorts based on Knuffle Bunny: a cautionary tale (2007) and Don't let the pigeon drive the bus (2010) have won Carnegie Medals. Willems has been involved in the production of various kits and animations produced by Children's Television Workshop, Sony Wonder and Weston Woods, and contributed to John Scieszka's Guys write for guys read. He currently lives in Northampton, Massachusetts, with his wife Cheryl and family. For more information see his website at http://mowillems.com.
General note
Published Works:
Don't let the pigeon drive the bus!, New York: Hyperion, 2003.
Dodd CLC D948
Time to pee!, New York: Hyperion, 2003.
Dodd CLC D1806
Knuffle Bunny: A cautionary tale (New York: Hyperion, 2004)., New York: Hyperion, 2004.
Dodd CLC C1036
The Pigeon finds a hot dog!, New York: Hyperion, 2004.
Dodd CLC D1819
The Pigeon has feelings, too!: a smidgeon of pigeon, New York: H. B. Fenn and Co., 2005.
Dodd CLC A4585
The Pigeon loves things that go!, New York: Hyperion, 2005.
Dodd CLC A4584
Time to say "Please"!, New York: Hyperion, 2005.
Your pal Mo Willems presents Leonardo, the Terrible Monster, New York: Hyperion, 2005.
Dodd CLC D1303
Don't let the Pigeon stay up late!, New York: Hyperion, 2006.
Dodd CLC D1820
Edwina, the Dinosaur who didn't know she was extinct, New York: Hyperion, 2006.
Dodd CLC D1805
You can never find a rickshaw when it monsoons, New York: Hyperion, 2006.
Dodd CLC A4493
I am invited to a party!, New York: Hyperion, 2007.
Dodd CLC C4983
Knuffle Bunny too: A case of mistaken identity, New York: Hyperion, 2007.
Dodd CLC D1790, CLC D1804
My friend is sad, New York: Hyperion, 2007.
Dodd CLC C4981
There is bird on your head!, New York: Hyperion, 2007.
Dodd CLC C4926, CLC 4940
Today I will fly!, New York: Hyperion Balzer and Bray, 2007.
Dodd CLC C4982
Are you ready to play outside?, New York: Hyperion, 2008.
Dodd CLC C5545
I love my new toy!, New York: Hyperion, 2008.
Dodd CLC C5510
I will surprise my friend!, New York: Hyperion, 2008.
The Pigeon Wants a puppy, New York: Hyperion, 2008.
Big Frog can't fit in: A pop-up book, New York: Hyperion, 2009.
Dodd CLC D2495
Elephants cannot dance!, New York: Hyperion, 2009.
Naked Mole Rat gets dressed, New York: Hyperion, 2009.
Pigs make me sneeze!, New York: Hyperion, 2009.
Dodd CLC C5911
Watch me throw the ball!, New York: Hyperion, 2009.
Can I play too?, New York: Hyperion, 2010.
Cat the Cat, who is that?, New York: Balzer and Bray, 2010.
City dog, country frog, New York: Hyperion, 2010.
Dodd CLC D2636
I am going!, New York: Hyperion, 2010.
Knuffle Bunny free: an unexpected diversion, New York: Balzer and Bray, 2010.
Dodd CLCD2634
Let's say hi to friends who fly, New York: Balzer and Bray, 2010.
Time to sleep, Sheep the Sheep!, New York: Balzer and Bray, 2010.
We are in a book!, New York: Hyperion, 2010.
Dodd CLC C6078
What's your sound, Hound the Hound?, New York: Balzer and Bray, 2010.
I broke my trunk!, New York: Hyperion, 2011.
Should I share my ice cream?, New York: Hyperion, 2011.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials dating from Willems' childhood to 2007, with correspondence, artwork, photographs, notes, manuscripts, moving images in the form of films and tapes, toys, fan mail, and publications. There are also several puzzles, sketchbooks, and materials created during his college days. The collection also contains a small drafting table used by Willems and annotated with the books he used the table to create.
The collection contains non-English publications by Willems, to include Chacun son tour!, Corso di pipi, La lecon de danse, Le pigeon veut un petit chien!, and Stuur die duif op tijd naar bed! Among the materials related to the English language books in the collection are materials from his Elephant and Piggie series, the Pigeon series, the Knuffle Bunny series, and many of his other publications.
Other subjects in the collection include Mo Willem’s book club, the Hermit, an early MTV pitch, You Can Never Find a Rickshaw When it Monsoons sketches, college scripts, his Sheep in the Big City show, failed pitches, early bad book ideas, Elmo's work titles, and materials related to 9/11 and the White House.
Arrangement
Series I: Inventory ( undated, 1965-2007 )
Bibliography
Mo Willems is a prolific author and illustrator who continues to add to his body of work. For a complete listing of his publications, see his web site at http://mowillems.com/.
Acquisition Information
Mo Willems began to transfer his materials to the Northeast Children's Literature Collection in 2008.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to children's literature and associated artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Willems, Mo.; Animators.; Authors, American --20th century.; Authors.; Books.; Children's literature --Illustrations.; Children's literature, American.; Correspondence.; Illustration of books.; Illustrations (visual works).; Illustrators.; Manuscripts.; Motion picture film.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photographs.; Publications.; Sketches.; Videocassettes.; Works of Art.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1965-2007
  - Correspondence, prints, moving images, artworks, notes, photographs, publications, clippings, administrative records, circa 1986 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    [Subjects include: comic strips, cartoons, evaluations, grades, early childhood, scripts.]
  - Books, publications, clippings, fliers, photographs, prints, notes, realia, correspondence, sound recordings, artwork, optical disks, moving images, 1988-2001 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: college scripts, sheep promo and press, early films, art pottery slides, off-beats, record pix, early press, book catalogs.]
  - Correspondence, moving images, print materials, clippings, books, notes, manuscripts, artwork, fliers, undated (Box 3)
    [Subjects include: press, fan mail, early books, printouts.]
  - Notes, manuscripts, artwork, correspondence, undated (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: off-beats, 'Around the World' sketches, college scripts, Normals comic strip, failed pitches, sheep production bible, early bad book ideas, Elmo's work titles, post-college correspondence.]
  - Prints, correspondence, books, notes, undated (Box 5)
    [Subjects include: book printouts, Pigeon (I, II, III, IV), Leonardo, Knuffle Bunny (I, II).]
  - Correspondence, prints, artwork, postcards, notes, manuscript material, posters, 1965-circa 1986 (Box 6)
    [Subjects include: pitches and rejections, illustrated essays, the Hermit, early MTV pitch, ideas for advertisements, old letters, old scripts and skits, YAK meeting notes, sketchbooks.]
  - Prints, correspondence, notes, artwork, undated (Box 7)
  - Realia, artwork, notes, photographs, correspondence, publications (books?), moving images, circa 1995 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: art, puzzles, Sesame Street boards, KND script notes, Sesame Street photos, maps, puzzle roughs, tiles, post college art projects, comics, off beats, Geography guy photo.]
  - Realia, posters, clippings, publications, artwork, correspondence, awards, transcripts, photographs, optical disks, notes, 2003-circa 2007 (Box 9)
    [Subjects include: Sheep toys, random book press/publicity, keychains, fan mail, illustrations, Mo Willem’s book club, Sheep in the big city promo, comics, KND feature outline, Sesame Street, planners.]
  - Moving image, circa 2002 (Box 10)
    [Subjects include: Sheep in the big city episodes, Sesame Street.]
  - Correspondence, prints, artwork, notes, galley-proof/book, books, financial records, moving images, 1988-1998 (Box 11)
    [Subjects include: childhood comics, off-beat boards and scripts, travel notebooks, odd publications, marked-up “Rickshaw” script and images, travel sketches, Tommy’s coat, the Helicart, September’s Day Off, Betty-Anne’s Glasses, Pilgrim, promos.]
  - Moving images, 2000-2002 (Box 12)
    [Subjects include: Sheep in the Big City.]
  - Moving images, notes, transcripts, 1988-1999 (Box 13)
    [Subjects include: early comedy, early sketches, Sesame Street, films, tapes, Misfits: Shoes, Big Bag, the Normals, the Sterile Yak goes casual, frequently asked questions.]
  - Optical disks, moving images, 1994, 2000 (Box 14)
    [Subjects include: cartoons, animation, whole career, ‘life’, Sheep in the Big City, Suzie Kabloozie, Seymore the snail, “An Off-beats Valentines”, Festival of Animation, the International Tournee of Animation, Rugrats.]
  - Correspondence, postcards, notes, photographs, awards, publications, clippings, artwork, fliers, 1994-circa 1998 (Box 15)
    [Subjects include: post-college illustrations, comics, nada calendar, McKee writing notebook, Promethius college project, the Normals, letters from 1990-1991 and around the world, nominations, 9/11 White House & letters, college cartoons.]
  - Awards, books, clippings, correspondence, ephemera, illustration, optical disks, posters, publications, realia, sketches, 2000s; 2010-2011; 1.38 Linear feet (Box 2012.0030_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects include: Boston Book Festival, CDs- "The Off-beats" "Park Slope Parents: The Album Vol. 1" "Stationery 2004-2005", Chicago Tribune- Play, Children's Literature (non-English)- "Chacun son tour!" "Corso di pipi" "La lecon de danse" "Le pigeon veut un petit chien!" "Stuur die duif op tijd naar bed!", The Elephant and Piggie Books, Forbes Library, Harper Collins Children's Books, The Helen Hayes Awards, Hyperion Books for Children, The Kennedy Center, sketchbooks- "Essential Reference Guide to: Monsters in Underpants" "Float" "The Red Truck" "Stamp Portraits" "Wise Things", Spider- The Magazine for Children, Time- for Kids.
  - Drawing table, 1987 (Other Object)